### **Ericka Smith Howard**

(425) 308-7120

ericka.smith.howard@gmail.com erickasmithhoward.github.io linkedin.com/in/erickasmithhoward

#### **SUMMARY**

Data scientist experienced with machine learning, statistical modeling, communicating business insights, & coding. **Expertise in:** Python (NumPy, pandas, scikit-learn), R (Tidyverse, Shiny dashboards), H2O, AWS, SQL, HTML. **Toolkit:** GitHub, Excel, EC2, Jupyter Notebook, PyCharm, PuTTY, GIS, AWS, Snowflake Data Cloud, S3

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

#### **Data Scientist**

Hartford Insurance Group

04/2022 - current

- Transform large data sets into actionable business insights using predictive modeling and machine learning solutions, including gradient boosting machines, A/B testing, random forest, logistic regression, power analysis, statistical tests.
- Use Agile methodologies to deliver analytics support and modeling solutions to business partners, including the use of data visualization and automation skills to translate technical findings to diverse audiences.
- Build and monitor advanced machine learning models in Python, used in the deployment of novel sales strategies that effectively target and prioritize profitable customers in real-time production settings.

### **Associate Data Scientist** Hartford Insurance Group

05/2021 - 03/2022

- Independently created, delivered, and monitored a machine learning solution that optimizes sales agents' efforts in outbound sales, including the exploration and implementation of enhancements for significant costs savings.
- Evaluated advanced statistical techniques and concepts to manipulate data and draw insights from large data sets.
- Collaborated closely with interdisciplinary team to produce analytical solutions to influence pricing and underwriting capabilities for insurance product, incorporating key stakeholders' feedback and goals.

#### **Research Assistant**

Cooperative Institute for Marine Resource Studies

06/2020 - 12/2020

- Leveraged data cleaning skills & discipline knowledge for analysis of large, messy datasets.
- Researched & implemented clustering algorithm to solve a data grouping problem.

Intern

National Oceanic & Atmospheric Administration

08/2020 - 11/2020

• Automated data management processes in R, resulting in a dramatic decrease in process time & a reduction in errors.

#### **EDUCATION**

M.S. Statistics Oregon State University

03/2021

Teaching Assistant: Methods of Data Analysis (Graduate Level), Intro to Statistical Methods

Coursework: Probability, Computing, & Simulation; Data Visualization; Comm& Line Analysis; Python;

Sampling; Survey Methods; Generalized Regression Models; Time Series; Unix/Linux

B.S. Math/Biology

**Western Washington University** 

06/2015

Employment: Database Assistant using Excel & Access; STEM Tutor teaching R & Excel

Coursework: Computer Programming & Data Structures; Differential Equations; Linear Algebra

### **PROJECTS**

## Classification Using Satellite Imagery & Random Forests 12/2020 – 03/2021

• Built simulations training many random forests, compared accuracy with different hyperparameters.

# **Bootstrapping the Pacific Crest Trail in Parallel** 10/2020 – 12/2020

• Tested use of socket method of parallel processing workflow to efficiently manage bootstrap resampling & simulations.

# Interactive & Explorative Web-Based Tool for Communication of Large Ensemble Models

01/2020 - 07/2020

- Honorable Mention (2<sup>nd</sup> place) nationwide from the American Statistical Association.
- Designed dashboard and visualizations to analyze high volume datasets and communicate ensemble models to technical & non-technical audiences.